Hello everyone. Uh, this is, uh, week, uh,
three open source circular fashion,
and we are going to have a helpful tutorial, uh,
for the workflow for, for designing, uh,
for os circular fashion for laser cutting from Claudius Mon.
Hello everyone. Welcome to this, uh, new tutorial. Uh,
we start us sharing my screen and
with a little presentation picking up from what we saw yesterday,
also from the lecture of Zoe. So, um, of course,
the objective of this week will be coming up with a series of, uh,
zero waste or modular design and de distillations. Uh,
there will be of course, uh, laser cut. Uh,
these are called also seamless pattern.
They will be open source and uploaded afterwards on our platform,
which is called o fashion.com,
where you actually can already browse, um,
wide range of patterns and creation from previous uh,
students in the Fabric Academy. Uh, if you click on each of them,
you can actually see, um, the materials recommendation, the processes.
So it's actually a way to learn from the others downloading the
pattern, and also experience this kind of way of,
of assembling and dis assembling different modules to create bigger, um,
further creations. Uh,
of course, so you can also see the new updates and the new, um, additions.
I also suggested during this week, uh,
most of you will be already able to take nice pictures and upload, uh,
um, your files along with documentation pictures.
I also want to pick up from what, uh, uh, done yesterday.
So of course this is gonna be the workflow. Uh, we're gonna start, uh, also, um,
later on today with a couple of software to experiment with digital design.
We also saw from last week that we're gonna mainly basically use the vectors
since we're gonna use the laser cutter.
This is an example from past student to see, um,
how from two D we're moving towards a real assembled garment.
Uh, this, of course, it's completely zero waste. Uh, I would say, yeah,
software is a matter of workflow, so it doesn't really matter which, um,
vector design based program or three D modeler you're actually using,
all of them are gonna lead you, uh,
to the objective of the week, let's say. Uh, and you can actually, um,
try to blend them together and, uh,
create this collaboration between Vector, but also the model software.
So of course, for the ones that are more familiar with vector based design,
I would, I would recommend, uh, to keep going with Illustrator on Inscape,
the open source version, uh,
but also Fusion in terms of parametric modeling actually is helpful
if we want to start, uh, uh,
thinking directly in the real size of the government. So for the scale,
one to one is actually, uh, my recommendation and of course,
rhino or better software for the ones that are already a little bit familiar,
uh, with this kind of software. Uh,
I think the example here of Susanna from a couple of years ago in France, uh,
actually, um,
breaks down all the steps that lead to this, uh,
interwoven kind of, um, tapestry. So, um,
I think most of our work this week will be definitely on finding a great
inspiration.
And I would say the one of Ani is actually the best example to also showcase,
um,
how this inspiration can be translated from paper all the way to a zero waste,
uh, design from the laser catheter. So, as you can see here, for example,
there's a zero squares.
So she was actually able to redesign where she saw in a temple
translate to paper, and then afterwards onto felt minimizing all the waste,
uh, as much as possible. But also the machine times,
uh, we saw yesterday a little bit, there are the principle behind,
but it's good to keep in mind that there's are also, um,
they all relate to each other.
So of course we are talking about a lot about zero waste, um,
modular fashion tessellation, and also, um,
seamless interlocking garments.
Uh, they're just, uh, um, little inspirations speaking up from yesterday to, um,
just give some comments about best practices, uh,
joins, uh, looking at the students of last year, for example,
that was an example from Moldova. Uh, I think we can,
we can align how sometimes even we have a very basic pattern,
which is actually a repetition of this itself. So just a circle. Uh,
we can still, uh,
work a lot on how these pieces can be assembled together to create even three D
structures, or two D and three D that combine at the same time.
And here is actually interesting how this bag is actually able to close itself.
Um, I put some keywords here on top. So, uh, for example,
also, uh, simulations are tools that are help quite helpful for this week.
Um, this is using, I guess, a vector software like, for example,
illustrator and already playing inside the software,
um, is also a way to,
to think in terms of shape and assign different colors will lead you to, um,
explore further the way in different ways of configure and
reconfigure, uh, the shapes that you have, uh,
layering is another technique. So in this case, um,
we also saw it previously and in the past tutorial, uh,
so we are moving from more, uh, let's say geometrical shape into more, um,
fluids and organic ones. So of course, uh, inspirations can be, uh,
also flower nature.
And in this case is also interesting to see how in one single cat,
one single journey we can actually interlock two or more pieces together.
It also depends, of course, on the thickness of the material, but also, uh,
on the pattern. Adjo itself, uh,
wanted to say that also a zero waste approach, um,
can be applied to a larger sheet. For example,
there is example of ve from Barcelona of last year, uh,
where this is of course completely zero waste is not made of different models
together, but still, uh,
there is one single pattern then you can see here at the bottom,
and it's just, uh, uh,
printed out with the laser on top of the sheet.
So the result is this, uh,
kind of collapsible structure that you can actually wear as a dress.
Um, I'll share the slides later so you can actually, uh,
press on the link and find all the documentation attached.
I think upcycling is also a key word for this week,
and there was an example of Hanin, um,
a couple of years ago here in tech works that she was up cycling, um,
a very big curtain from the house that was made in velvet and getting inspired
from sea creatures.
And the ocean was actually able to work, um,
to testate this kind of curtain. Also using the edge,
not only just the front of the back of the pattern,
but also the thickness itself to create this kind of vertical, uh,
configuration. So if you explore this, for example, on a circular fashion,
you can also find the booklet with all the different steps.
And this is something that can be also nice if you're able to, and, uh,
if you manage to upload it during the week,
another technique can be related to the kigami, the Japanese of art,
of, uh, cutting a folding paper. And this is the,
I think the best example is given by Tiana.
Then she was clearly spied by the hadid and architectural shapes to
combine a joint together with a pattern. So here the bottom, again,
there is a nice example, uh, of join.
And one single module repeated can actually, actually, um,
create this kind of deed, uh, an interesting configuration,
um, for the ones that are already
also suggest to keep going and explore, uh,
different sliders and possibility. That was the work of a tool, um,
from tech as well a couple of years ago.
And I think here is nice to see how she, um,
added this kind of parameter of density.
So she was controlling the space in between the different gons.
And again, if you click on the picture, you gonna see, uh, the full exploration.
Um, one topic also to, um,
that service to be talking about is to engineer the joint,
um, taking top count, for example, the, uh, thickness of the material,
but also the shape you can always improve, um,
how the two pieces are connected together, or the three pieces.
So this is an example of might where you also see, um,
how she moved from connecting two pieces all the way to apply, um,
and cloning a single joint on different part of one t-shirt to create, uh,
different interwoven configurations trend, not, uh,
completely symmatic, for example, from the front or the back. So in this case,
for example, she's using a sheet as a playground.
So she has kind of agreed where the,
she can play with positive and negative spaces. Uh,
joints can also be decoration. We have many examples in the students. Um,
a favorite of mine, I think is this one, is the moon faces, uh,
clearly inspired by, um, by the moons.
And I think it's interesting how, um,
Anna in this case was translating and redesigning this kind of, uh,
um,
configuration on the moon into a pattern to be used as a join.
And even connecting bigger sheets together,
um, joins can also relate to branding, for example.
And this is the case of a Lara campus, where you saw on first time, um,
um, introducing, let's say the, um, concept of storytelling. So it's nice.
Uh, I would say the drawing can be shaped by two different element.
And we have a female and a male, for example. Um,
the moment interlock each other. They're actually able to compose and represent,
uh, um,
a logo or an interesting design that can be applied in specific parts,
um, of a sheet, uh, of a poncho and example in this case, uh,
a fish or a logo of the project. So that was a pon that was, um,
raising awareness about ocean. So I also leave you the link, uh,
to explore further the story. Uh,
personal grids can also be explored. And, um, modular heritage, I think, um,
at least for this lab here in tech works is a topic that we,
every year we explore.
This is the final project of Miam that was actually born during the assignment
of the third week. And here's,
so the way she brings the community inside the project, um,
recreating the Palestinian embroidery in a more, um, digital way.
So for example, she could use the same grid for, um, other different patterns.
And she also crafted, um,
this kind of collections clearly inspired by our own heritage.
Um, of course you saw the example of Allah, and it's also, um,
great example of engineering the joints and also, um,
imprinting this kind of storytelling all over the project.
So as you can see here in this leaf, um,
he was shifted from a pure square pattern, uh,
all the way to embedding different, um,
motives that were typical from Mary fashion history.
So she was starting, um,
just having a plain read of squares and then step by step iterating,
uh, in some parts. For example,
here already you can see this kind of flowers or the sun,
and all of them go back to the traditional dress code of secretions.
Um, last pattern list. Uh, it's also possible to include different materials.
So we also, um, invite you to explore not only connections,
but uh, um, for example,
you have something to upcycle that can connect somehow to your design or can be
integrated. And here we have, um,
a great example from the bootcamp we had it made this year that was made by
participants, um, completely from scratch.
We upcycle this kind of bedwin tent. Uh,
it was a large sheet available at the lab, so everything is actually, uh,
zero waste. The base was square, um, and the rest is gold. That was, uh,
in the wall here, uh, at the lab. Um,
I'm going back one second to Ellation. And of course,
yesterday we had learned that was a process of fixing the shape together,
of tiling completely a plane without gaps of, um, overlapping.
Uh, Asher, uh, was the master in this.
And now we are actually able to do, uh, ourselves in a matter, uh, of seconds.
So we are actually able to decode, uh, this kind of patterns going back to math.
And there's a nice way, uh, there also space on the grid,
space on angles, space on pure math. It's the same one that applied to every,
for example, Arabic patterns and also, um,
uh, all the dramatical ones all over the world. Um,
here is a schematic also made a clear, for example, into colors
or what we can actually see, uh, a little bit later.
So either Inscape or Illustrator can actually create, uh,
configurations like this for the ones that want to explore, uh, zero waste,
um, uh, pattern. For example, for the fabrication,
this is something clearly important that basically through principles to take
into account. One, is it isation through translation? That means,
uh, we have a starting point. This can be, um, a square, for example.
And what happens on top, uh, we take it to the bottom.
What happens on the right, we take it to the left.
So if I export apart from the square and I drag it all the way to the bottom,
we do the same thing on, uh, from left to right,
and I basically have a shape
that I can clone onto different rows and create a pattern.
We're gonna have a little, uh, look later.
And the same thing happens, uh, for example, on the base of triangle.
So in this case, we can rotate a shape and applying this, uh, uh,
like a triangle. So 60 degrees,
we can have a shape that teates and completely fills,
uh, our plane.
This again, was done illustrator, and follows the same workflow.
There is a nice, uh, online generator,
and I bet there are many others that you can find, um, just browsing online.
Uh, here you can just play with a given shape,
like a triangle rectangle on gon, and by editing the corners on the edge,
you actually able automatically to, uh, create this kind of, uh,
patterns into colors or three colors. So it's also, uh,
very good to get the first, uh,
steps into the words of tessellation. Of course,
you can explore your own grid and also create different innovations for
many patterns. And
the moment you really apply to colors is the moment you can see, uh,
not only the single module, but the big picture.
These are another example. Also, um, put a link. Some refers to papers,
some refer to nice tutorials. There is also,
um, a nice one in Inscape. We had a big last time,
so I'm not gonna show Inscape, but we directly moved later.
I leave you the link here, so you can just click and see. Um, it's, um,
it takes, uh, for example, 10 minutes steps to create something like that.
This is through, uh, command cloning. So basically what happens,
and the way you modify one single object, the moment is, um,
connected to many others.
All the transformation that you apply to one single line will be applied, uh,
accordingly.
We're moving to the directly Themic note. Um,
I think I will start with fusion here. Just, uh, a couple of slides to drop.
What I'm gonna do, um, in one.
So fusion is a three D.
Parametric modeler is one of the best to control parameters and also
to establish relationships between the elements, uh, in a design.
Um, that's the first exercise, I think. Uh, also the first, uh,
feeling that you can have creating this kind of patterns.
So usually we start creating a female and a male and explore the way they
connect between each other. Um,
either software fusion or either, so, um, sorry,
fusion or rhino. Uh,
give you the possibility to save the sketch. Uh,
the design as as a vector.
So as a P D F or DAF for, for the nesting, for example,
and illustrator on scap.
And one thing to keep in mind is, again, like, uh, the digital body.
So of course we're talking about, uh, um, our g b space.
We're gonna use, for example, the red as a standard color to cut.
So the hundred 55 0 0 is the code for the red and
0.1, 0.01 millimeters.
It's gonna be the stroke that we applied to all the pieces that we want to cut.
Um, as you learn previously, this is called nesting,
and that's a way to kind of ate and organize the space.
So we minimize the waste as much as possible. But also the machining time.
We saw yesterday a little bit that, uh, it's a good way to start simple,
having a female and a male connecting, uh, each other,
but also we can always iterate it.
So there is also a way to combine that them together in a single module.
Or I can also have other additive friend shapes to use, uh,
in combination with them. Mm.
This again, if you are a bit familiar with Illustrator and vector file, uh,
well drawing yourself,
it's a good way to explore and simulate beforehand different kind of, uh,
patterns. I think it's also fun to see, um,
how they overlap
and what they can create in digital world.
They all follow a female plus male connection, and the design will change,
uh, according to the shape,
but you can also add three or four, uh, connection.
Of course, it's gonna be just a little bit harder to visualize this. Uh,
in a two D space,
I think I can move directly to, um, fusion,
and I hope you can still see my screen. Um, I'm using a Mac,
so if you're using a Windows, the space may be a little bit different.
Uh, this is basically the interface. So the moment you, uh, launch Fusion,
you're gonna have, uh, uh, this in front of your eyes.
You have a dashboard that you can always, um, collapse here on the left.
And this is how appears the empty file, um,
fusion works, um, like different, uh, parametric software.
Basically where we start from is creating a sketch.
The sketch is our two D plane. So to begin with, we,
we click on the first cycle, which is called exactly Create Sketch,
and we select the top of the cube. Of course, I can always rotate the view,
and I just click to enter. This is what we call sketch mode. Uh,
the first icon, okay, I do it, uh, uh, again,
and the moment I actually do it, and one icon here, the button appears.
So this is my, um, sketch recorded in the timeline.
So, um, if I want to go back,
basically I double click on the icon and enter the sketch mode again,
further control z i, it is what it,
and I exit. Again, the sketch mode.
There are so many shortcuts on the keyboard that you can use, uh, with Fusion,
uh, like many other software like Rhino, for example. So, uh, suite, again,
we create a sketch. I click on the icon and I click here on the top. Now,
I use set of tools on top, uh, will be in front of my eyes. So for example,
we want to start creating this, um, two circles,
a male and female interacting each other for laser cutting. So, um,
as I can see here on top, I already see, uh, tools, um,
toolbox. I can see a circle and I can, I can also find them here.
I can specify if I want them, uh,
to be starting from the center or from the point I usually start, um,
from the center. It's just, uh, a personal preference and I can specify it,
uh, whatever on this grid I wanted to replaced. So again,
I can click on the icon, I click anywhere I want to, um,
the circle to be on my grid, and I click and I release.
Um, if the ship is blue, means is a closet loop,
I do it again. I click on the circle,
I click randomly and I release it. Uh,
fusion, as we said earlier, is a nice software, um,
to work with dimensions and relate relationships between different parts of the
design. So, uh, this is gonna be, uh,
a good friend of yours, uh, sketch dimension or d in the keyboard.
We'll help you assign a specific value to a shape or to a design. So,
um, again,
if I click on D or Sketch Dimension and select the edge of my shape,
I'm actually able to give a value to this. So for example, let's say, um,
of course I'm working in millimeters.
This is something you can specify in the preferences.
So let's say I want this to be 60, this is my six centimeter circle, uh,
created. And like Rhino,
I can only say even afterwards that I want this to be instead five,
uh, centimeters, and I can just, uh, double click on the value and change
the measure, change the dimension. Um,
there is a better way to do this, to assign this kind of values,
and it's gonna be here under modify. So, um, usually,
and this is can be also integrated in your workflow, uh,
you go to modify and click on change parameters.
And this is the place where you can define your, um, values. Um,
you can give it a name, you can give it an expression or just a number.
So for example, I want, uh, if I have many polygons,
I can call it edge and I can give it, for example, 60 millimeters.
I can give it a comment or not, and okay, just to create it here.
Every time I want to change any value,
I just double click on the number and my dimension will change accordingly.
Um, I create another one. For example, I call length.
I can use it for my edge, uh, or to define another specific, uh,
dimension. And I can, for example, um,
20, so two centimeters,
and I basically lead them here. The moment I want to modify them, again,
I go to, uh, front top, modify and change parameters, and I have them here.
So I can change now this to edge and still, um,
the function, it says it's 50. I can also, for example,
say I want this to be, um, edge divided by three.
So now of course this is gonna be 20. Contrast it, I'm fine with 60.
Um, then, uh,
there's a nice tool here on top confusion in the menu,
which is the constraint and the sketch palette. This is where, um,
you can actually assign relationship between different lines and shapes in your
canvas. Um, let's say we want to create this kind of joints.
So there will be basically, um, simple cuts.
That means lines where as a cutting, I usually start creating, um,
access that, uh, actually will not be part, uh, for example, um,
of the design. To do so, I will be clicking on the line.
And if you are over with a mouse, you near some points, for example,
you can see sort of snaps. So fusion is already, um,
sensing somehow that here, there is a straight line.
Here is the limitation of my edge,
that I can specify a point here along the curve. So as you can see here,
I'm able to see a straight line. I can just go and create my access.
I click, I click the second point, and I confirm here with, um,
escape on the keyboard, I escape the selection. So now nothing is selected.
Uh, I can decide my axis to be part or not, or my design.
So if I leave it as it is now, I can see I have two different closet loops.
So if I laser cut this, I'm gonna end up having a circle split into,
uh, to avoid this,
I click on the edge or any line I want not to be part of my design.
And I sign, uh, construction type here.
So now my access is not interfering at all with any of the shape.
So for example, we can say, um,
let's try to create this, um, female connection.
So now I have an axis as a reference point,
and I can go on this, uh, middle line of the circle to place. For example,
my first, uh, uh, connection.
I want this to be exactly in the middle so I can use any access I want to
specify, uh, directions, but also dimensions. I, again,
I click a random line 'cause I prefer to sign the value later.
That means that I can go to create and again,
sketch dimension. So I want the, this one for example, to be, uh,
can say linked for example, by, uh,
split by two. So it was 20, now it's done.
And I'm doing this just to show you a couple of commands. So for example,
there is a mirror here,
and you can also find it under their needs. So
in a similar way of right now,
fusion is telling you what are the objects that you want to mirror and which is
the mirror line. So of course we need to have something in between.
And I do it again. I click on the object. I went to mirror. Um,
here the software is telling me one is selected,
I click on the mirror line and I also get a review in real time.
So now I have mirror my line and fusion is adding this
kind of icons to remind me I did, I did this.
Uh, now that I have already defined my female, let's say I want, uh,
all the circle be full of, uh, female connections and these kind of lines.
Uh, of course there are many ways to do it there. You can always copy paste it,
you can clone it. Um, you can it,
but you can also create a pattern so you don't have to do double job. Um,
you can create under create. Here you can find a command, for example,
it's a circle. So circular pattern I create,
I select the line I want to repeat,
and like before I need to select a certain point,
the center of my circle. And then I'm able to, um,
as I can see here in the preview, to specify the number of,
say repetition of my line and create equally spaced
different cuts. For example, you want, we're happy with four,
we want them to be, you know, even three to make it a little bit different.
And now, uh, the moment we press, okay, we have this kind of pattern,
uh, repeated to be sure this is, uh, also recorded. Here we have the icon.
So the moment I want to change this,
and I'm not okay anymore by having three by one, four,
I can just go here and update my design. Um,
the moment I click, I click finish my sketch. This is the,
the result if I want to make any change again. Now this is kind of blocked,
so I have to go back in the sketch mode and I can see here on top because
there is this, uh, tool. And again, I can make, uh,
any change to my design. I want five,
I want three, or I change my mind. I want this to be
30. So everything now is basically accordingly.
So of course they won't fit.
I can go back and specify in another dimension.
And now my connection is, uh, uh, spaced in a different way of,
of course I only, uh, specified the parameter here. I'm still able to move this,
uh, along the middle point because I don't have, I didn't have specified, uh,
distance between the center and my line.
So if I want to be a hundred percent precise,
I already have clear idea on how my final shape, my final pattern is gonna be.
I can also, uh, place the last constraint.
So now my design is gonna be fixed and I cannot actually, uh,
play around by dragging and um, my shape all over the counter.
So to do that, I do create sketch dimension,
and from the center to any of the point of my line, I can place,
um, my value.
So I want this to be 2010 and everything will be
spaced accordingly. Or again,
I can create a new parameter and I connect this somehow to the other.
I can say edge, multiply two,
it's quite too big.
So now it gives me also the name of the value is placed by five, maybe
three, and I kind of got more or less, um, the same one.
Uh, here on the menu,
you can find in the folder with sketches and your own sketch.
So the moment everything is, um, your sketch is selected, hidden,
you can also see the, um, your design coming in below, uh,
double click. You can also, um,
enter again the space or double click at the bottom.
And of course right click, you can rename it the circle
or you can just proceed to save as d xf.
How do we make the second, for example, so we made the female, we can make, um,
the male part. Uh, there are again, many ways to do it.
To do it. Um,
we can start simple by copy pasting everything. So just, uh, selecting, um,
doing, uh, contrast C, control V or right click move,
move copy is together. So two contrast, C contra V.
And I can have a copy of my design. So I can use actually this,
uh, as a pattern. If we're doing something very simple at the beginning,
this is very suggested to do so. Uh,
the best practice will be keeping the same distance for the female of the male
consistent. So if we want to just have,
um, nice, uh, tight, um,
stable joint between two shapes, we can just create for example,
uh,
the lines in between here until the meta circle or
even continuing the line all the way outside of the shape.
And then introducing, for example, um, commands like streaming rhino.
And the moment you select the icon,
you are actually able to delete the lines.
You don't want to be part of the design, of course, uh,
some parts may of the design may be linked to the previous one.
So the moment you delete some lines, you are deleting, uh, some constraints.
They were previously linked,
say we're still, uh, exploring the software, that's fine. So, uh,
I'm not actually caring of that. I just want you to, um,
to show you that I can do the same thing I did before.
So if I don't want these lines to be part of my design,
I just get rid of them with dream.
And then I create instead the pattern to replicate, uh,
the main part.
So I go back to create a secure pattern.
I select the lines,
a certain, um, center point,
and already I can see a preview of what's gonna happen if I
answer two, three or more, uh, lines. So now
there's a way of having
a female and a male part gather. Of course, again, this is not, uh,
linked. So, uh, the moment I move, um,
I need another dimension to fix this imposition. So I do it again.
I create a secret pattern,
I create the lines I want to replicate all over.
And now this tool, for example, match,
I can get rid of the axis. So for example, if I'm exporting this, um,
anywhere will not be part, will not consider as part of my design.
And if I'm quite happy with the result, I can uh, just finish my sketch.
I can also select everything. I can select,
also move and bring this too closer if I'm thinking of nesting everything
in fusion, uh, if I want to do that,
I can also select everything together and instead of the squeal pattern,
create a rectangular pattern. So all my design will be automatically replicated,
uh, on different draw
according to my, uh, to different parameters.
So I can also add more.
It depends on my needs,
of course, like before now, I left some overlapping, but uh, in this software,
everything is, uh, is recorded and everything can be adjusted. So I just go back
on the icon of my pattern. Sometime I have too many,
I just have to find the right one with, with somewhere.
Of course, the country did z uh,
undo and redo are also here on top.
And it was apply to to many software.
I don't see the icon. Just do it again to show you.
So from create angular pattern, I select the ones I want to, uh,
to clone. I can put five,
I can select also the direction
and the space. Either, uh, inserting a value,
just uh, using the snap function.
So this is kind of, um, let's say isolated 'cause it's a waste,
not really, it's a circle.
So of course you are gonna end up having this kind of space in between the
shapes that you can decide to reuse it or not for your design, for example.
So the moment you end up having something like this, uh, some less over,
you can also think of, uh, why not creating again,
I dunno, an axi here
and then a couple of joins. Then you can just, uh,
even copy paste or pattern all over and then replicate through a pattern
and apply to, to all the sheet.
Let's say we want to use another software this time to better, um,
nest the shapes. So now I can call this, uh,
female male circles
and I can proceed to export it so I can save them as the XF
next top. Okay, circles in place
and I move to illustrator.
Illustrator is a vector file is a, sorry, is a vector software from um, Adobe.
The moment you create a new file from file, new document,
this is how the interface appears. Um, I always put,
especially because in the lab here,
we use illustrators also to communicate with the, so for example,
so for example, I always put, uh,
the dimension of the bed of the laser cutter here,
and I decide I want this port to be around one meter by 600 millimeters,
which is exactly the dimension of the bed. Uh, I want one airport, uh,
orientation will be horizonal and the color mode will be, uh, R G b.
I don't need this. My skin is 6 72, so I can keep this, uh,
as a default for the next, um,
explorations. So this is how, um,
the interface is here the moment I create a new document and
I always begin enabling the rules here on top.
So with the Ctrl R common R I'm able to create this, uh,
enabling them magnetic rules that I can just, uh,
drag and drop on my account to, um,
snap things to the grid or have a better understanding
on how things, uh, uh, can be placed. Um, on my sheet
I can import, for example, or you can just, uh, even open,
um, my circles.
Okay? Okay, it's not this one
circles.
I might have already one called circles, so I can do it again.
Um, okay, so two,
this is my, I can just do open with illustrator and I always,
um, choose one-to-one original size and, uh,
be sure your design wants to be to be in millimeters.
Uh, so this is how from fusion got exported. One thing,
the moment you export from a three D model to,
to a vector file to consider is also, um,
if there are double lines or not.
I created this lines infusion by metering each of them
separately. So of course now I don't end up with a single line,
but in administrator, uh,
I can always easily get rid or join lines together.
Through that, I select the two lines. For example,
I one to join and I select, um,
from the keyboard Command J or control J.
So now everything is, uh,
this is only one line that I'm able to move around.
I do the same for all of them, Sol,
JL J. And uh, this might be left over from Axis,
so I actually don't need them, but if I want to proceed, uh,
with the laser cutting for this, I can just, uh, uh, list them.
For example, I can group them, group G
and I can apply, read a stroke for one, uh,
0.1 millimeters.
I double click on the stroke in my color here.
I be sure this is, uh, web colors, R G B,
and I just put red,
so I always be sure here is red 255, 0 0,
and this is the standard. If I'm not actually able to see my design,
I can apply a different stroke for the moment.
And now it's a group. So I'm actually able to move them, um, around.
And Illustrator is quite easy to nest shapes together. I,
I can do, um, for example, from the keyboard,
there's many shortcuts to work with this, uh, vector based software. So, uh,
if you press for example, um,
alt or option for Mac and you drag and drop one shape,
you're actually able to create, um, a clone of them.
And if you keep pressing shift, you can move
on the same direction. So one axis is actually locked, so I'm not able to move,
uh, up and down, but I can only go straight. So you can see here
I'm selecting the group. I previously, uh, did and I select,
I click on my keyboard alt or option. I select the couple
and I space it. I have also from the settings, the snaps, uh,
enabled.
So I can also find easily what are the tangent points or
when two points meet, um, in my design,
I do it again. And there is, uh,
once I do this,
if I want to have it done and ate kind of sating my full
port, I can also, uh, from the keyboard repeat this, uh,
command, uh, pressing command D, orl D.
So control D is allowing me to, um,
to repeat the previous command. So the moment I press it in my keyboard,
and actually to have the full row in just one second,
and now I can just do the same thing. So I can select
I clip the old row, and again, I can do, um,
the moment I click alt or option in my keyboard, I have this, uh,
icon here of the two others together. So I,
I press command, uh, sorry, I press all two option I,
I press shift together so it doesn't move. And again,
I keep doing, uh, command d,
CTRL D to have my completely add select sheet.
Now we can see the last drop example. Um, it doesn't fit on my laser cut bed,
of course, I was assuming to have, uh, a full board.
This won't be the case for most of the projects.
So we probably end up adding something like this. Uh,
I go back,
I select everything with common A control A or just selecting
with my mouse. And again,
I just apply a stroke to B 0.1 millimeters.
And at in, I make sure where my lines are here
to be sure that also you end up having a closed loop.
So the laser is gonna actually create a circle and you'll be able to export
the material outta the board.
You can just reverse the color and the moment, um,
you, you feel the color is shaped from the stroke, you can actually,
uh, have the confirmation that you are being, uh, that you have a closed loop.
Um, if there are questions about this, I think you can just, uh,
unmute yourself and speak up. 'cause I'm not able to see the chat. Uh,
otherwise I leave it here.
And I just do what I was promising earlier in the slides. This there, um,
that ation, so I have another art board here. I can just create it,
um, through this icon. It's called the art board, or just, uh,
create a new document. And again, adding a new, uh,
sheet through the icon, I can just
enlarge or make it smaller. So let's,
illustrator is a, is a bit friendliness. It's, uh, quite helpful
and I do in a similar way as I was doing in Fusion, I create a shape.
So as you can see here,
you have a palette with different tools for to d design.
I can see if I keep pressing, I find a square, a lips, polygon,
et cetera, et cetera. So I want to start, uh,
with a simple one. So I click on the rectangle, or as you can see here, uh,
m in the keyboard. So I click it and I have two options.
Again, I can select the first point and release it.
So, uh, now I have no idea what my size is.
I can go, for example,
to shape and transform and see and control it from here. So there are these,
this, um, say menu here that you can, uh,
even drag and drop it closely to your canvas.
And you can also specify a number here. So for example, again, 30,
but also 50 60, if that matters,
or the moment you click up square,
you can click anywhere and assign from scratch, uh, dimension.
So you end up having, uh, exactly the same result.
I'm not working with the stroke, so I have it. My shape field,
this is just an example of the installation.
So I'm using this square just as a base, and there is, uh, this nice,
uh, very friendly alignment tools that I hear on top.
So I always be sure my design is actually at the center of my, my canvas.
And again, I can, uh, create an axis. If I click on my shape,
I see this kind of bundles, uh, kind of everywhere, especially at the mid point.
So I can just drag, uh,
the magnetic rule here in the middle and create Canva axis.
And then again, we're trying to do what we saw earlier in this slide.
So if something happens on top, we're gonna happen at the bottom and vice versa.
So from left to right or right to left, uh,
I have many tools that I can choose from in the palette here. I can also, um,
use this that are called, uh, Pathfinder,
something similar that you saw in the in rhino to combine different shapes
together, but also to subtract them,
I can really do, um, whatever I want so I can, uh,
keep iterating my shape from the edge, uh,
with a pan, for example, and joint.
So my shape would be composed of different points. Uh,
we can subtract things, we can, um, use the pan, we can use the,
another polygon. So example, I, I can add a circle.
Uh, let's say we can, we saw the polygons ready, we,
we can try to use the pan. So pin the keyboard or the pan icon here,
and you can create, um, by just clicking
different points. I do it again.
You can actually place them whatever you want. This is just, um, a test.
So then create, uh, something like this.
If you don't see what you actually did, you can change the color by click
on your color. So stay, want this to be blue,
actually make it more simple. Stay on the line.
I do something else. Uh, for example, on the other side.
So the moment I'll also click with the pen. I, uh,
if I open with the mouse next to a point,
this will be highlighted kind of a anchor.
So I can also place easily just napping my, uh,
pen here.
And now I have, uh, two slightly different loops.
So for example, I can, uh, select the two I want to,
um, interact and intersect with. And I select the two ships that I made.
And I, for example, choose any of the pathfinders.
So I didn't know if it was clear. Um, I select the two of them.
I want to apply the a transformation on. So the, the, the red and the blue.
I click on this icon, it's called divide.
So basically I'm gonna have a split.
This by default comes in a group. So I can also use, uh,
right click and do ungroup. And basically I already have this done
if I want to do it again, I can also select them both and do okay,
join them together. As long as they intercept a little bit,
the sub is able to merge them or split them. Um,
if you have a split into, so like a line or a shape itself.
So I split it and I can, uh, put it here for example,
and I can do this way, um, join this two
automatically. Uh, you know that it's joined because, uh,
the new color of the second shape is adopted.
So redo this will be a menu new shape.
So it is just one. And again,
what happens at the bottom up in the top, up at the bottom,
while my shape is not totally, it's not very amazing, I can also,
um, for example, manipulate,
applying kind of a feel it or angle to modify. Furthermore, the shape,
or if I click on the second arrow here, I'm actually able to, uh,
double click on the vertex and manipulate again, uh,
in a different way, my shape.
And here again, I can do, um,
many things. Um, once this is done, I'm quite happy with that. Again,
I can do the same or can just do, um,
copy paste it or like we did before, we drag it down,
making a copy. So clone it with option or alt all the way down.
I can also select everything and hide it.
So I'm actually able now to see, uh,
that I copied and then I can do it again.
This is gonna be subtracted
and this is gonna be added. So
this is gonna be part of the same shape and
I can try to put this down.
So right click, uh, let's range it to the back.
So I'm actually able to take the second,
give it a color just to distinguish the two of them. And we can say, I,
I want to subtract this. Uh, again,
I can get rid of the axis and now my shape is kind of defined,
so I can just clone it and see how perfectly this
is. Uh, desolating my space.
Again, I select everything
I can space or I can just drag and drop them.
Of course, you can really be precise with a snap.
The moment you have to.
You can also be sure
this is not very precise. You can also click, um, on a certain point.
So you're actually able to snap the pixel.
We want to be sure you apply just the stroke and not the feeling.
So everything is cleaner. And I want to type your listing.
That is basically sometimes when you have closed loop and patterns,
uh, like in this case, you really want to optimize also the machine time.
And, uh, sometimes you are gonna have,
especially if you nest the pieces like this, uh, a double line. So you have
this edge is gonna be replicated on top of this one. So in most of the cases,
useful to know, um, a command called cut in your,
you can access through it, um, by clicking here, the scissors.
So if you just click on two different points,
you're actually able to break the loop and get rid of the double line.
So now your partner will be, uh, let's say more correct.
And again, you can just, uh,
take the pixel and move it on the way back as it was before. So again,
this, uh, is gonna be in common.
So I can also get read of this one.
And now I kept, I can keep cloning my button all over.
I can repeat the same
and even transform and join, um, together in only one line,
all the bottom lines and all the, um, top lines together.
And then I can do the same, of course, I can also do it at the end. I delete,
uh, all of them. I create a new line, uh, a new continuous line.
So many designers will be, uh, much more clean also in terms of, uh,
fabrication. Then again,
I can apply a stroke. Can,
I think pick it from here or double click on the column.
So it is gonna be red again, 2 55, 0, 0.
Of course,
I can group everything even here now with the a integrated
ai. Or I can also, uh, manipulate it.
So I can definitely scale it up or down the
color. I can also do, um, a couple of things
more or just, uh, say I'm happy with the design and in order to finalize it,
I can just apply this back to be 0.1 millimeters
and, uh, of course save it and export, for example,
as a P D F or any other vector file for
in case illustrator in your case is connected directly to the laser.
You can just go to print and send it to, um, draw,
uh, job control or any of the software there. So
again, I can just do export as
even S V G circles. Two export.
You can keep the default here. Of course, it says vg.
So now you know that there is actually a code and, uh,
press okay in your documentation. You can link it as a,
as a file as a P D F again, or daf. You can just, uh,
put it in the files folder, uh, inside the documentation.
So your file is gonna be placed here.
I actually selected, um, everything.
So both of the boards will be in our part of my big design.
Um, we can quickly move, uh, onto Rhino just to, um,
quickly see the difference between Fusion. Uh, again,
this is Rhino version on the Mac, so it might be a little bit, uh,
even more than little bit maybe different from Windows.
But of course the commands are the same.
There is a top menu and there is a side one. Uh, we're gonna use,
um, mostly just the comments that you see here. And I think to begin with,
it's good to light that. Uh, as you can see here, uh,
on the left is a good practice to have most of these, um,
snap enabled. So, uh, when you saw before,
when I go nearby a line or, um, certain shape of my mouse,
I really want to, um,
to be sure I click onto a specific pixel on a specific point.
So I'm gonna keep, um, the end point, the midpoint,
the center intersection,
and as a default in my design. Uh,
and we can try to do something similar that we did, uh, with Fusion.
So now we're gonna see the difference of between a parametric modeler and, uh,
a software like Rhino that handles geometries. Uh, but not only, uh,
we can do an example with squares rectangle, for example. So,
uh, this is the interface we'll be working on, and this is my view.
I don't have to click like fusion, uh,
already from the beginning on my top front, uh, or left,
uh, through this icon I can see altogether.
So what happens here is gonna happen, uh, in the front and in the right,
of course, at the respective views and also in the perspective.
I can click on any of them to zoom, zoom mode to see if they're, um,
connected. And I can just, uh, click on the top.
'cause I'm gonna work basically into this. So this is the, um,
always be sure you're working from the top side.
Uh, again, we can create a rectangular in a similar way of fusion.
So clicking on the icon here, and I can just, uh, uh,
rhino is telling me, uh, where to begin. So what are the coordinates? Where,
where is my first point gonna be on the canvas? Um,
I'm trained as a product designer,
so of course my plane also is gonna be, uh, for example, um,
coordinate. So I usually begin at the center, um,
of my grid that is actually given here. So I just input zero, um,
common zero as my origin. Uh,
and I create, um, basically can, I can specify the length,
the edge, the corner. So I can also say, again, this,
have it 60 by 60 as a square,
and I can be sure this actually 60, uh, by looking on top.
And I can go on dimension.
I can see there is a command called liner dimension.
And I can see from here to here, this is actually 60.
Um, it is a bit misleading. It is not like fusion,
so it doesn't work, uh, like that.
I cannot double click and change the value accordingly. I can also just, uh,
debug and verify that my dimension is actually six centimeters.
Of course. Uh, please, if your line is not a millimeters,
go back to uh,
five and explore the dissecting and be sure this is at two millimeters more.
'cause we're dealing with, uh, small objects, but also, um,
0.1, 0.2 millimeters, especially for this week.
Um, so again, this, I, I found it on the, uh, dimension,
Leonard dimension, and I just click, um,
couple of points to specify my distance.
Um, there are many ways, of course also RiNo to create something like, uh,
these patterns. We can start, um,
creating an access, for example. And again,
we can see here that according to the snaps that we selected,
we can have sort of guidelines. So if I go closer to the edge,
I can highlight the mid mo.
So I can just click here and create a line all the way here.
I can confirm through the keyboard and escape or the arrow.
So to escape any selection,
I can also choose, for example, to ignore the axis and just proceed, uh,
creating a line like we did before.
So again, I'm gonna use the quality line. I can create
placing one point first, and then the second a line,
if I already know the value, it's, it's gonna be easier for me to know.
So again, we can set two 20.
So I can place the first point somewhere and just say,
I want this to be 20.
Okay?
If I want to the back just to make sure it's 20, again,
I access two dimension and click on linear dimension and select two points
and is actually 20,
I don't really need this and I can just delete it. Uh,
united is a nice way to, um, organize.
So I can just move this around or through the gimbal here, the shapes,
uh, to place this correctly, let's say at least, uh,
at the middle here of my axis, I can also
select line. I want to move
right in the command line, move more curve.
And since I have this alighted, I don't need the center now,
can keep the point midpoint.
I just need to see exactly where the midpoint is so I can move from point to
point, from point to edge, from the middle of this
to any place, any location I want this to be. So for example, here
again, I don't really need these lines, so I can just get rid of it.
And again, I can create a similar way like we did fusion, uh, a pattern,
a circular pattern. So as you can see, uh, the software really doesn't matter.
The workflow is mostly the same. Uh,
you can select the line and write, um, array in, um,
every software as a different, um, um,
set of rules and commands that you can choose from. Um,
you can start typing something and, uh,
you can also already accessing all the different, uh, commands here. Uh,
I'm gonna use the one called the ray polar. So, um, right now,
again, it's telling me, um, to specify what I want to do. So,
uh, I can also begin with the command and then, uh,
afterwards just selecting the line so I can write again, array color,
select objects to array. I press enter when down.
So most of the commands will work this way. And,
uh, the center, I'm lucky enough to have it here. So I,
well, I deleted the access, so I actually needed it. I go back in time.
Fortunately, uh, that's allowed.
I go back to click my line first or just input the command again.
Um, rhino, if you press, um, backspace,
um, the space bars are in your keyboard,
you can actually repeat the previous command. So it's just easier, um,
to work with keyboards sometimes in this kind of software. So again,
select objects to array is gonna be my line.
And turn one down and specify the center.
So this is gonna be in the center. And uh, again, similar to fusion,
how many items we want to put. Previously we added three.
Now we're gonna go for four. So when I'm done,
I used to confirm and I can specify the angle.
So it's gonna be all over circle.
So three under 60 degree, I press it here
and here is my, uh, preview. So I'm happy with that. Yes,
I clicked on, I,
I can just get read the, um, the other lines that I don't need.
Of course, again, to create the male part or a combination,
let's say of female and male part, uh,
you can do chondro CDL V and clone the same one.
Um, there are many ways to do it. For example,
we want to have the other connections here, similar to um,
this shape and the vertical part.
So Aino can actually do something like this. I can just select the two lines.
I can, um, continue the line so I can, uh,
um, select this kind of icon.
I can decide to scale a factor in wide direction if you already know.
Or I can just, uh, uh,
let them go all over the shape in case I need to trim the line
intersecting with other lines
and trying to do something like this. I can actually do, um,
copy paste. I can create a pattern later to get my, my, my shape.
There are many ways to do it. I can also, uh,
create a line here as a reference and then some instead of
copy pasting, for example, I can do similar like, uh,
opposite of set care and I can decide,
um,
the distance or point to point from this one to the,
to the other point, like this for example.
So I just opposite one line. That means I moved, uh, at a certain value,
my line to have reference, and now I can just decide to, um,
to have it part of my design or not. I can also add it if I want.
And through this icon actually able to, to put it back,
I do what I was doing before.
I can also move it a little bit through this scheme,
but I select them both. I want them to be, uh,
not part now of my design. They can create some confusion.
I choose to continue the lines this way.
And now I want to know where actually my lines were.
Okay, so for example, uh, I want to, I want to trim it.
Basically I had
Something like this here. Now, um, I'm trying to make,
as you can see here in the object, uh, the other parts I can just, uh,
intersect with the female part. So it's gonna be a module, uh,
that has together female parts like these cats and male at the same time.
So, uh, in an or and in a different way from fusion,
from uh, uh, a better way of math in a more,
let's say I'm still brainstorming my shape. I just, uh,
exploring different commands. So that's so kind of allowed.
Uh, I can use trim again if I don't know where's the icon,
it's gonna be here,
but I can just more comfortable sometimes with the trim now that I have lines
intersect with it's intersecting between each other. I can just, uh,
side which kind of lines I want to trim. Um,
I want to remove
basically the lines here in between and just leave this part. So again,
I can select, um,
the command again and the software is telling me select the cutting object.
So, um, I want to create something like this.
The two lines horizontal will be my cutting object.
Press enter one down and select the objects you want to dream.
So I want to dream the ones here.
And again, I do the same thing or can just, uh,
shorten the others that I really don't need. So again,
space bar trim and I can do the same.
So select the cutting object. This one enter,
and again, I can decide
to make it shorter to remove a line that I don't need.
And basically this is what I plan to do.
So I have a square that is together, male part, female part and male part.
And of course I can also, if I want isolate in rhino, uh,
for some reason the moment I try to copy paste, uh,
my copy command is not disabled for this kind of version. So, um,
I always try to play around and do offset
and I can also, uh, select on the curve I want to offset.
Yeah, it works the same, but usually I'm just more comfortable in, um,
and that's what I recommend to do, um, this kind of, um,
nesting sation in none of the software either scape or
illustrator. So I can just go, uh,
and tell Brian when I'm done with my design tool export,
the maybe last thing that we can do here in the software,
you can select everything and be sure also here in this layers
panel to um,
adjust the line or laser cutting. So we're ready in, uh,
R G B space, we can make sure also clicking on the layer.
Uh, here we have, uh, line type. So we have to be sure this is continuous.
We have a default. This is the call we want to set to red.
So let's be sure here we can put R R G B 20,
um, 55 red.
And also if this helps you to visualize the thread, you can actually, um,
select this and change the appearance of the layer itself.
So now it's gonna be hundred percent the appearance and uh,
um, the attribute of the color red, of course, um,
you can scale, you can decide a point
or percentage or a distance. So example here,
you want also to play with um, scale.
I think Rhino is a very good software to do that.
Or you can scale repeating the command. For example,
from this point, you can input a number like eight centimeter.
Now it's gonna be bigger
or et et cetera. You can rotate it,
you can combine other polygons, other shapes. You can create,
um, other female connections.
So the more like cuts you have inside of geometry, for example, the more,
uh, room to play and intersect different modules you have.
Um, and that's it I guess. So again,
last thing and just go to file. Of course,
I also recommend you to enable the automatic savings.
So every once in a while I know we'll do this job for you.
You don't have to be worried of losing any file and we can just, uh,
export selected if just you want that. Of course. Um,
I have two different license. Um, I'm not using the correct one,
so I am not able to export it, but uh, the workflow is gonna be basically, uh,
testing of the other software.
I think I can stop, um, screen sharing
and um, check the chat or uh, just want to um,
speak up in case you have questions. I hoped it was quite clear,
I dunno if you were trying at the same time to do it with me or, um,
I raised any other doubts
I also have here in front of me, for example, some of the examples.
So that was the one in the slide we talked about.
It was a big sheet that was recycled in a modular
assembly that was, um,
a bag made of different squares together. So basically this is what we did.
Now in the, in the software that actually takes, uh,
the moment you start practicing around 10 minutes,
20 minutes to deal with these geometers, again,
you can see them as a pattern. So the moment you have one line,
you can array on pattern the same line all over the edges.
The same happen for, um, the circle.
So that was a female part connecting to
a male part. Maybe it's more clear from the back.
You can see this sort of arrows connecting inside.
If you are able, after you test your shape to do this kind of test, like, uh,
cool and stress, that means that uh, your joint is actually quite stable.
It can just move forward, um, to is cutting.
So if that's okay,
of course the moment you have four at the moment you have eight,
that's gonna be way much more stable.
That's a similar, um, for the circles.
And I also have an example of what we saw before through the kigami,
for example.
So there is one part which is a female that includes inside
a male part. So I don't need an extra sheet, an extra pattern.
I can just flip my connection and inserted
onto another shape, which is basically the same without this one.
So I use the connection inside, sorry, my background.
Okay.
So I can just combine this two together
and uh, I end up having this kind of, uh,
empty space, negative space that can actually be, uh, helpful
to create something
or same but different.
That's a little part that can be also isolated in another way,
but still as the same exactly connection of this one.
So I can also say I want to use, uh, an extra material,
an ex an extra pattern with a different, uh,
inch with a different connection to connect the, um,
two shapes in a different way or to display something in the back.
So I always try not to think just in the front.
Sometimes the most interesting part is actually the one that you're not planning
to pattern or to display.
Uh, also the example that I showed before in terms of the grid.
So sometimes you might actually, um, um, want to create a,
you have a bigger sheet and you want just make use of that.
So you can have something like a
small laser cut lines that uh,
can be like a playground and you have just this kind of arrows that can be
insert to display. Like a picture,
like a bigger picture in this case was a big pattern.
But you can also have like on those stripes more like a woven technique
visualized.
And of course you don't have material yet, but you want to experiment. I also,
um, challenge you to play to play a little bit with paper.
If which paper doesn't work,
it is not gonna work on oxide because paper is more or less, uh,
similar materials.
So either in terms of flexibility or properties is um,
quite similar. It's quite stiff. It's more or less the same thickness. So,
uh, this kind designs can also is an example of my past student who, uh,
got covid two years ago during this week. So she actually did assignment, um,
with fever, um, by hands, not the laser cutting.
So everything is actually possible and uh, can be interlocked.
Of course we do not recommend it. Um,
but it's uh, a good way to, to get the feeling of playing with material.
Of course, you, if you're limited and you don't even have, um, colored paper,
let's say you are end up, um,
coloring the little space in between just to distinguish the shape.
Now also there are many tools, AI and, uh, et cetera,
et cetera that can be incorporated in work workflow. So,
um, just, uh, very much looking forward to what, uh,
you're gonna explore this week.
And you can always build upon what's been done in secure fashion
and uh, play with uh, materials connection.
Uh, I have a question. You just talked about, uh, incorporating ai.
How, um, exactly are you, uh, thinking of that? Just like, uh,
visual inspiration or, or is it something
Yeah, just can be done. For example, I had a student I think, uh,
last year that she actually did that. Um,
maybe can describe machine, my screen just um, um, here. Um,
yeah, that's exactly what I was thinking of. So, um,
in terms of reference inspiration, for example, she was using, um,
she wanted to do something in the direction of a pixel art. So she was actually,
um, trying through, um, the ai, um,
to get some inputs in terms of, um, visuals she had. Um, oh, okay,
okay. Great repository for that. Um,
then she decided not to use actually, um, any of them.
And the result is actually, uh, something that,
so before in this slide, so
some people just use, um,
the tool to get more inputs on the configuration or how different, um,
shapes mm-hmm. Can be overlapped together. Okay.
To create things. And of course if you look at the documentation also of, um,
of dine in terms of variations, you have, um,
a great brainstorming phase. Okay, thank you.
I don't know if there were questions before. Okay. No,
the kid to the dentist. Um, it's okay.
This session is recorded and, um,
here's is the slides. So you can already,
for the ones here at least have a big, uh, presentation. Uh,
get back to me on master most or, um, do any of us with, uh,
troubles. Otherwise, um, we wish you'll have exploration.
Thank you. Thank you.
Bye everyone. Bye.